This is a kindergarten we designed in 2007.
هذه حضانة أطفال صممت في 2007 .
We made this kindergarten to be a circle.
و قد قمنا بتصميمها على شكل دائرة
It's a kind of endless circulation on top of the roof.
دائمة الاستداره على قمة السطح
If you are a parent,
فإذا كنت وليّ أمر
you know that kids love to keep making circles.
فأنت تعلم أن الأطفال يحبون عمل الدوائر
This is how the rooftop looks.
و هذا ما يظهر عليه شكل السطح
And why did we design this?
فلماذا قمنا بتصميمه على هذا النحو
The principal of this kindergarten said,
حيث ذكرت مديرة هذه الروضه
"No, I don't want a handrail."
"كلا، لا أريد درابزين "
I said, "It's impossible."
فقلت أنه من المستحيل
But he insisted: "How about having a net sticking out from the edge of the roof?
ولكنها أصرت وسألت" ماذا عن عن خروج شبكة من حافة السطح؟
So that it can catch the children falling off?"
وبذلك ستحميهم قبل السقوط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I said, "It's impossible."
فقلت: أنه مستحيل
And of course, the government official said,
وبالطبع ذكر المسؤل الحكومي أنه
"Of course you have to have a handrail."
لابد من وجود الدرابزين
But we could keep that idea around the trees.
ولكن يمكننا تنفيذ هذه الفكرة حول الأشجار
There are three trees popping through.
فهناك ثلاثه أشجار تخرج من هناك
And we were allowed to call this rope as a handrail.
كما انه مسموح لنا باستخدام هذا الحبل كدرابزين.
But of course, rope has nothing to do with them.
ولكن بالطبع, لن يستطيع الحبل عمل شيء حيالهم
They fall into the net.
لذا. فقد سقطوا في الشبكه.
And you get more,
و تحصل علي المزيد
and more,
و المزيد
more.
و المزيد..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sometimes 40 children are around a tree.
فأحياناً تجد 40 طفلا حول الشجرة.
The boy on the branch,
الولد فوق غصن الشجرة.
he loves the tree so he is eating the tree.
و لأنه يحب الشجر فكان يأكله ،
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
And at the time of an event,
و في وقت الحدث،
they sit on the edge.
يجلسون على الحافة.
It looks so nice from underneath.
حيث تبدو رائعة من الأسفل.
Monkeys in the zoo.
القرود في الغابة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Feeding time.
وقت الطعام.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And we made the roof as low as possible,
كما جعلنا السطح منخفض قدر الإمكان،
because we wanted to see children on top of the roof,
حيث نود رؤيه الأطفال على قمة السطح،
not only underneath the roof.
ليس فقط أسفل السطح.
And if the roof is too high, you see only the ceiling.
و في حاله الإرتفاع الشاهق للسطح، سترى السقف فقط.
And the leg washing place -- there are many kinds of water taps.
كما يوجد أنوع عديده من صنابير المياه ذو
You see with the flexible tubes,
أنابيب مرنه بأماكن غسل الأقدام.
you want to spray water to your friends,
أو رش الماء على أصدقائك
and the shower,
أو الاستحمام
and the one in front is quite normal.
أما هذا الذي بالأمام يبدو طبيعي جداً
But if you look at this,
ولكن إذا نظرت إلى هذا
the boy is not washing his boots,
الطفل لا يغسل حذائه،
he's putting water into his boots.
إنه يضع الماء في حذائه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This kindergarten is completely open, most of the year.
فالروضة مفتوحه معظم أيام السنة
And there is no boundary between inside and outside.
كما أنه لا يوجد حد فاصل بين الداخل و الخارج.
So it means basically this architecture is a roof.
لهذا فهذا يعني أن هذا المعمار هو السطح
And also there is no boundary between classrooms.
كما أنه لا يوجد أي فواصل بين الفصول
So there is no acoustic barrier at all.
فلا يوجد أي حواجز مضاده للصوت على الإطلاق
When you put many children in a quiet box,
فعندما تضع العديد من الطلاب في صندوق هادئ
some of them get really nervous.
فبعضهم يصبح عصبي جداً
But in this kindergarten,
ولكن في هذه الروضة
there is no reason they get nervous.
لا يوجد أسباب للعصبيه والتوتر.
Because there is no boundary.
حيث لا توجد حواجز وحدود.
And the principal says
لذا تقول المديره:
if the boy in the corner doesn't want to stay in the room,
إذا وجد طفلاُ في الزاوية، لا يريد الجلوس في الفصل،
we let him go.
سندعه يذهب
He will come back eventually, because it's a circle, it comes back.
في النهاية، سوف يعود لأنها دائره.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the point is, in that kind of occasion,
ولكن المقصد أن الأطفال عادة يحاولون
usually children try to hide somewhere.
الإختباء في مكان ما في مثل هذه المناسبة
But here, just they leave and come back.
ولكن هنا، سيرحلون ويعودون مرة أخرى
It's a natural process.
إنها عملية طبيعية.
And secondly, we consider noise very important.
ثانياً، نعتبر الضوضاء شيء مهم جداً.
You know that children sleep better in noise.
كما تعلم، الأطفال ينامون أفضل في الضوضاء
They don't sleep in a quiet space.
لا ينامون في الأماكن الهادئه.
And in this kindergarten,
و في هذه الروضة،
these children show amazing concentration in class.
يبدي هؤلاء الأطفال تركيزا مدهشا في الفصل
And you know, our kind grew up in the jungle with noise.
وكما تعلمون، أن هذا النمو يترعرع في الغابة مع الضوضاء.
They need noise.
فهم بحاجه إليه.
And you know, you can talk to your friends in a noisy bar.
وتعلمون أيضاً أنه يمكنك التحدث مع أصدقائك في الحانة الصاخبة.
You are not supposed to be in silence.
من المفترض أنك لن تكون في هدوء.
And you know, these days
وكما تعلمون، أن في هذه الأيام
we are trying to make everything under control.
نحاول السيطرة على كل شيء.
You know, it's completely open.
كما تعلمون، فهي مفتوحه تماماً.
And you should know that
و يجب أن تعلم أنه بأمكاننا
we can go skiing in -20 degrees in winter.
الذهاب للتزلّج في 20 درجة مئوية تحت الصفر شتاءً.
In summer you go swimming.
وبإمكانك الذهاب للسباحه صيفاً
The sand is 50 degrees.
حيث تكون درجه الحرارة 50 مئوية.
And also, you should know that you are waterproof.
كما أنه يجب أن تعرف أنك ستكون مقاوم للماء
You never melt in rain.
فلن تذوب في المطر.
So, children are supposed to be outside.
ومن المفترض أن يكون الأطفال بالخارج
So that is how we should treat them.
و يجب أن نعاملهم بهذه الطريقة.
This is how they divide classrooms.
و يقسمون فصولهم بهذه الطريقة.
They are supposed to help teachers.
فمن المفترض أن يساعدوا المعلمين
They don't.
لكنهم لا يفعلون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I didn't put him in.
لم أضعه به
A classroom.
الفصل
And a washbasin.
و حوض الإغتسال.
They talk to each other around the well.
يتحدثون مع بعضهم البعض حول البئر.
And there are always some trees in the classroom.
وغالباً ما يوجود بعض الأشجار داخل الفصل.
A monkey trying to fish another monkey from above.
يحاول قرد الإمساك بقرد آخر بالأعلى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Monkeys.
قرود
And each classroom has at least one skylight.
كل فصل لديه نافذه سقف واحده على الأقل
And this is where Santa Claus comes down at the time of Christmas.
حيث تنزل سانتا كلوز وقت الكريسمس
This is the annex building,
هذا هو ملحق المبنى
right next to that oval-shaped kindergarten.
مباشرة بجانب الروضة بيضاوية الشكل
The building is only five meters tall with seven floors.
يبلغ ارتفاعه 5 امتار بسبعة طوابق
And of course, the ceiling height is very low.
وبالطبع فإن ارتفاع السقف منخفض جداً
So you have to consider safety.
ولذا فيمكنك اعتباره أماناً
So, we put our children, a daughter and a son.
لذا، فنضع أطفالنا، الإبن والإبنة.
They tried to go in.
يحاولون الدخول
He hit his head.
صدم رأسه
He's okay. His skull is quite strong.
هو بخير. فجمجمته قويه جداً
He is resilient. It's my son.
إنه مرن. إنه إبني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he is trying to see if it is safe to jump off.
فيجربها ليعرف إذا ما كانت آمنه للقفز أم لا
And then we put other children.
ومن ثم وضعنا أطفال آخرين.
The traffic jam is awful in Tokyo, as you know.
والمرور متكدس في طوكيو كما تعلم.
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
The driver in front, she needs to learn how to drive.
فتحتاج السائقة في المقدمة، تعلم القياده
Now these days,
و الآن، في هذه الأيام،
kids need a small dosage of danger.
يحتاج الأطفال جرعة صغيرة من المخاطر .
And in this kind of occasion,
في مثل هذه المناسبة،
they learn to help each other.
سيتعلمون مساعدة بعضهم البعض
This is society. This is the kind of opportunity we are losing these days.
إنه المجتمع. وهذا نوع من الفرص الذي نفتقده هذه الأيام.
Now, this drawing is showing the movement of a boy
الآن، يوضح هذا الرسم حركة الولد
between 9:10 and 9:30.
ما بين الساعه 9:10 الى 9:30.
And the circumference of this building is 183 meters.
فمحيط هذا المبنى 183 مترا.
So it's not exactly small at all.
فهي ليست صغيره على الإطلاق.
And this boy did 6,000 meters in the morning.
ويستطيع هذا الولد قطع 6000 مترا صباحاً
But the surprise is yet to come.
المفاجاة لم تأتِ بعد.
The children in this kindergarten do 4,000 meters on average.
يقطع الطفل في هذه الروضه 4000 مترا كمتوسط
And these children have the highest athletic abilities
فهؤلاء الأطفال لديهم أعلى قدرات رياضية
among many kindergartens.
بين العديد من رياض الأطفال.
The principal says,
تقول المديرة،
"I don't train them. We leave them on top of the roof.
"لن أقوم بتدربيهم" نحن نتركهم على قمة سطح المبنى.
Just like sheep."
تماماً مثل الغنم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They keep running.
حيث يواصلون الجري،
My point is don't control them,
المقصود هو عدم التحكم بهم،
don't protect them too much,
لا تحاول حمايتهم كثيراً،
and they need to tumble sometimes.
كما أن الأطفال بحاجة إلى التعثر أحياناً.
They need to get some injury.
كما يحتاجون إلى بعض الإصابات.
And that makes them learn
و بذلك سيتعلمون كيف
how to live in this world.
يعيشون في هذا العالم.
I think architecture is capable of changing this world,
أعتقد ان العمارة قادرة على تغيير هذا العالم ،
and people's lives.
وحياة الناس.
And this is one of the attempts to change the lives of children.
وهذه إحدى محاولات التغيير في حياة الأطفال.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)